this is the final video where we'll be
learning about the basic examples of
spinners in physics
in the last couple videos we've learned
how both LightWave polarizations and
Quantum spin States can be described
mathematically by pairs of complex
numbers called Spinners that rotate on a
sphere with su2 matrices
in this video we'll learn how to
visualize Spinners as flag poles on a
sphere and learn how Spinners are points
on the complex projective line
to begin let's review some of the basic
facts about Jones vectors and Quantum
spin State vectors
a diagonally polarized wave is made up
of equal amounts of horizontally and
vertically polarized waves
however if we phase shift the
horizontally and vertically polarized
Waves by the same amount all this does
is shift the entire wave along the axis
of travel
the wave is still diagonally polarized
so the polarization is unchanged
so we know that multiplying A Jones
vector by an overall phase does not
change the polarization
here's something else to consider if we
take a diagonally polarized Jones vector
and multiply it by two all this does is
double the amplitude of the wave but the
wave is still diagonally polarized
so the polarization is unchanged so
we've learned that multiplying A Jones
vector by an overall scaling Factor does
not change the polarization
so polarizations are unchanged when we
multiply a wave by any overall phase
factor or any overall scaling factor and
of course a scaling factor and a phase
together can be used to describe any
complex number this is just an
alternative way of writing a complex
number X Plus i y
so polarizations are unchanged when we
multiply Jones vectors by a complex
number
now let's look at Quantum spin states in
the stern gearlock experiment
we know that when we take a particle
with a given spin State and apply an
inhomogeneous magnetic field the
particle will exit the magnet as a
Quantum superposition of two outcome
states that are split in the up and down
directions I was a bit imprecise about
this in my last video but the states
doesn't fully collapse into the spin up
or spin down state until a measurement
is performed at a detector
the probabilities for collapsing into a
given state are given by the squared
magnitudes of the inner product of the
States before and after the collapse
this is called born's Rule
if we multiply our initial State vector
by an overall phase and then look at the
results of born's rule the complex phase
comes out and has a magnitude of one
leaving the resulting probabilities
unchanged
what this means is that any two State
vectors that are related by a complex
phase represent the same Quantum state
so Quantum states are unchanged by
overall phase factors
now let's consider multiplying a Quantum
State vector by the number two
in many introductory quantum mechanics
classes your professor might tell you
that this is not allowed because this
can give us probabilities larger than
one when we use born's rule professors
might tell you that it's required that
all Quantum State vectors must have a
length of one to ensure that the
probabilities of all possible collapsed
States add up to one
however we can actually allow Quantum
State vectors to have lengths larger or
smaller than one if we make an
appropriate change to born's rule
this new version of Bourne's rule
contains a division by the squared
Vector lengths which normalizes both
vectors to have a length of one
with the newborns rule we can feel free
to change the lengths of our state
vectors as we like as long as they are
non-zero because the newborn's rule will
normalize them to one for us
so if we multiply the first state vector
by 2 we get a factor of 2 squared in the
denominator which cancels with 2 squared
in the numerator leaving the probability
result from born's rule unchanged so
it's only the angle between states that
matters not the lengths of the state
vectors
so with the newborn's rule multiplying a
Quantum State vector by an overall phase
by an overall scaling factor or both
leaves the state unchanged
so both Jones vectors for light waves
and Quantum State vectors in the stern
gerlock experiment can be written as a
pair of complex numbers
and both of these can be multiplied by
an overall scaling factor and an overall
complex phase without changing the state
they represent
we call these pairs of complex numbers
that don't care about overall complex
multiplication spinners
so we can write Spinners as a pair of
complex numbers Alpha and beta
these two complex numbers are made up of
four real numbers two scaling factors
and two phases
this might make you think that Spinners
require four real numbers to be
specified but since we are free to
multiply a spinner by any complex number
without changing it we can always
multiply by one over Alpha
causing the top component to be one and
making the bottom component the ratio
beta over Alpha
so really there's only one complex
number that's required to specify a
spinner since it is only the ratio of
beta over Alpha that actually matters
and this is a single complex number with
two real parameters
this is why we're able to visualize
Spinners as arrows on a sphere only two
real parameters are needed to specify
them the longitude and the latitude
the remaining two parameters the overall
phase and overall scaling are ignored
however we can still visualize the
overall phase and overall scaling if we
like using a flagpole visualization
instead of drawing a spinner as an arrow
on this sphere we can instead draw it as
a flag on a flagpole
the orientation of this flag on the
flagpole represents the overall phase
factor that we're ignoring we can also
change the length of the flagpole to
represent the overall scale factor that
we're ignoring so that it can be less
than or greater than one as long as it's
not zero
note that a specific spinner is only
identified with the point where the
flagpole meets the sphere so changing
the angle of the flag and changing the
flagpole's length do not change which
spinner we're talking about
we can see these factors mathematically
if we write out our spinner as a
combination of two basis Spinners each
with complex number coefficients
if we multiply and divide the second
term by e to the I Phi 1 we can factor
out e to the I Phi 1 from both terms and
bring it out in front
if we take the Spinner's magnitude to be
M we can multiply and divide both terms
by m then bring a factor M out in front
the ratios A1 over M and A2 over M can
be visualized on a triangle like this
A1 over m is just the cosine of this
angle and A2 over m is just the sign of
this angle
you'll notice that I've chosen to write
this angle as Theta over 2. this is
because in the original space the two
basis Spinners are 90 degrees apart but
on this sphere where we ignore overall
signs they are 180 degrees apart
so we need to take this angle on the
sphere and divide it by 2 to get to the
correct angle between the basis Spinners
in the original space
so we can rewrite A1 over M as a cosine
and rewrite a 2 over M as a sign
I'll also rewrite Phi 1 as Omega and
rewrites the phase difference Phi 2
minus Phi 1 as just Phi
so we've Rewritten our two component
spinner like this and it has four real
parameters M Omega Theta and Phi
the Theta and Phi parameters determine
where the spinner points on the sphere
Omega is the overall phase and
determines the angle of the flag on the
flagpole
and M which is the overall magnitude
determines the length of the flagpole
the Omega and M parameters can be
ignored since overall phases and overall
scaling factors don't change the spinner
only the Theta and Phi parameters matter
because they determine where the spinner
points on the sphere
as an exercise you can try calculating
the Theta Phi and Omega parameters for
this spinner of length one that's been
rotated around
and try checking that the flag
orientations make sense
so Spinners are pairs of complex numbers
where the overall multiplication by a
non-zero complex number doesn't change
the spinner
this probably seems very mysterious but
there is a way we can understand
Spinners better by realizing they are
members of the complex projective line
the complex projective line is a bit
confusing when you first see it so let's
start simple and look at projections in
the ordinary two-dimensional space with
real numbers which is the X Y plane
let's imagine that we have a vertical
screen at the position x equals one and
we want to project points onto this
screen
one way to project points is to send
them along parallel lines at right
angles to the screen
this is called orthogonal projection and
it Maps the point x y to the point 1 y
the y-coordinate stays the same but the
x coordinate is forced to be one after
the projection
with this projection objects retain
their true vertical sizes after the
projection
another type of projection is called
perspective projection for this we put
our I at the origin point and project
all points in the plane towards our eye
using radial lines
the locations where these radial lines
hit the screen are where the points end
up after the projection
with perspective projection the true
size of objects is not retained after
the projection
objects that are farther away from the
screen will appear to shrink more than
objects that are closer to the screen
with perspective projection all the
points on this diagonal line through the
origin will be projected to this same
specific point on our screen
we normally write the equation of a line
as y equals MX plus b where m is the
slope and B is the y-intercept
however since our projection lines go
through the origin we have b equals zero
and so the slope M of the line is equal
to Y over X
this is true for any point on the line
so all points on this line have the same
y over X ratio
if we look at the point where this
projection line crosses the screen at x
equals one we find that the Y value is
the slope m
so all X Y points on a given projection
line get projected to the point 1 M
where m is just the ratio y over X
so the destination point will be
completely determined by the ratio y
over X
this means that if we scale a point by
some overall scale factor a it will not
change its destination point after the
projection
all this does is push the point outward
along the ray
the scale factor will get canceled when
we take the ratio between Y and X so it
doesn't affect the final destination of
the point after projection
we call this space after the projection
the real projective line rp1
now there are a couple of important
details to consider with the real
projective line
one thing to consider is this point here
on the y-axis where does this point get
projected to on the screen
tracing a radial line towards the origin
the resulting Ray points downward
parallel to the screen and goes on
forever
so this point doesn't get projected to
the screen at all
we say that points like this get
projected to the point at Infinity
any point with a zero x value will get
projected to this point at Infinity
because the Y over X ratio involves
division by zero
this point at Infinity can be reached by
projecting downward along the y-axis or
upward along the y-axis so there is a
single point at Infinity that can be
reached by projecting infinitely in
either the positive or negative
directions
this point at Infinity sort of joins up
both infinite ends of the screen so that
it forms a continuous loop
this idea of a point at Infinity might
make you feel uncomfortable but this is
a perfectly valid mathematical object in
projective geometry
it's just an extra point we include for
projecting points parallel to the screen
just remember that all X Y points with
the same y over X ratio get projected to
the same point on the real projective
line
and in the case of X Y points where the
x coordinate is zero all of these are
considered equivalent and are projected
to the point at Infinity
although keep in mind the origin Point
does not get projected anywhere and is
ignored for the real projective line
the second thing I want you to consider
is the left half of the plane behind our
eye that's at the origin
it's important to remember that points
behind our eye will also get projected
to the screen
so if we look at this circle these two
points on opposite sides of the circle
will get projected to the same point on
the screen because they exist on the
same line on the origin
any two points on opposite sides of a
circle centered at the origin will get
projected to the same point on the real
projective line
the projection can't tell the difference
between the positive version of a point
and the negative version of a point
because in both cases the Y over X ratio
is the same the projection doesn't care
about overall scale factors of negative
one
so if we take a semicircle and project
all of its points onto the screen we'll
cover every single point on the screen
including the point at Infinity
watch what happens to the projected
Point as we travel along this circle
the projected Point goes off to infinity
and then comes back after a half turn
around the circle the next half turn on
the circle corresponds to another loop
on the real projective line
so one turn around the circle
corresponds to two full turns around the
real projective line
it's almost like the projection takes
the circle and makes it curl around on
itself so that it wraps around twice
instead of just once
so that's the real projective line we
put a screen at x equals one and project
all the points in the plane along radial
lines connected to the origin
the destination points are completely
determined by the ratio y over X and so
overall scale values don't matter
points on the vertical axis are
projected to the point at infinity and
points on the opposite sides of a circle
will end up projected to the same place
because projection destroys the
difference between positive and negative
versions of points
now it's possible to do this in higher
Dimensions as well we get the real
projective plane rp2 by projecting all
points in 3D space radially from the
origin onto a flat two-dimensional
screen at x equals one
in this case the resulting point on the
screen only depends on two real numbers
the ratio y over X and the ratios at
over X
we saw the real projective line is like
a circle with opposite points made
equivalent so it's like a semi-circle
where walking off one end teleports you
to the other end
the real projective plane is like a
sphere with opposite points made
equivalent so it's like a half sphere
where walking off the edge teleports you
to the opposite Edge
we can use a similar approach for real
projective spaces in higher dimensions
but let's get back to Spinners and
consider the complex projective line
the complex projective line is very
similar to the real projective line
except instead of dealing with a pair of
real numbers that are unchanged by real
number scaling we deal with a pair of
complex numbers that are unchanged by
complex number scaling
unfortunately it's basically impossible
to visualize a space of two complex
numbers because this would involve four
real dimensions
but the mathematical reasoning works the
same as the real projective line we
project our Alpha Beta points onto a
kind of screen located at Alpha equals
one
the position on the screen is entirely
determined by the ratio beta over Alpha
points that have a coordinate of alpha
equals zero will get projected to the
point at Infinity since this results in
a ratio of beta over zero although we
ignore the origin point when doing
projections
after the projection we can no longer
tell the difference between the positive
version of a point and the negative
version of a point because they both
have the exact same beta over Alpha
ratio
in fact we can't tell the difference
between any two points scaled by an
overall amplitude and complex phase
because these also go away when we take
the ratio beta over Alpha
the flagpole sphere is how we visualize
points in the complex projective line
with one of the sphere's poles being the
point at Infinity
the ratio beta over Alpha completely
determines the direction of the flagpole
on the sphere
we've seen this sphere called the point
array sphere and the block sphere
but in the context of the complex
projective line we call it the Riemann
sphere
if we go back to the six main Spinners
we've been looking at for the last few
videos you'll notice that they are all
completely defined by the ratio of their
two components
the spinner with Alpha equals 0
represents the point at Infinity
I'll briefly mention Mobius
Transformations which are General
matrices that act on a spinner
by treating the inputs and outputs as
single complex numbers given by the
ratios of the spinner components we get
this function here called a Mobius
transformation I'll talk about this more
in future videos
so we now have a good mathematical
description of what a spinner is it's a
member of the complex projective line in
other words it's a pair of complex
numbers that have been projected so that
the overall scaling and overall phase
Factor doesn't matter
it's only the ratio of the two
components that matter
the result of this projection is that a
single rotation in the original space
before projection results in two full
rotations in the space after the
projection
because in the projected space we can no
longer tell the difference between the
positive and negative versions of a
point
each point on the complex projective
line is determined by two real numbers
and so we can draw the points on a
sphere determined by two angles Theta
and Phi
if we want to visualize the overall
phase of a spinner we can view it as the
angle of a flag that is spinning around
a flagpole and the overall scaling
Factor can be visualized as the length
of the flagpole
but neither the angle of the FLAG NOR
the length of the flagpole change the
location of the relevant point on the
sphere and so they don't actually change
the spinner
so we've closed the first chapter of our
journey into understanding Spinners we
have a mathematical description of
spinners that works and can be applied
to two different physical problems but
there's still more to learn we'll see
later that we can write 3D vectors as
two by two matrices that rotate with
double-sided Transformations using a
pair of su2 matrices
if you're familiar with quaternions this
is equivalent to rotating a vector with
a pair of unit quaternions
we're going to see that we can Factor
this 3D Vector into a pair of spinners
and each spinner will rotate with a
single su2 Matrix
in other words Spinners transform with a
single quaternion instead of two
quaternions
we'll also see how we can find the
higher dimensional analogues of the
quaternions and su2 matrices
for example in the four-dimensional
space time of special relativity we'll
generalize the quaternions to The Matrix
Group sl2c which will allow us to do
both rotations and reference frame
boosts giving us six types of rotations
for space-time spinners
also I've left a few links in the
description to other sources that
discuss physical applications of
spinners and the flagpole visualization